Finding Aid for Margaret Bell papers, 1919-1956
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Margaret Bell papers 1919-1956
Bell, Margaret, 1888-1969.
6 linear feet
861055 Aa 2
Correspondence and other files of Margaret Bell, chairman of the Department of Physical Education for Women of the University of Michigan, and physician in the University Health Service. Materials relate to University activities, conferences and speeches, copies of articles and other writings, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received form Mrs. Karl Illava on December 16, 1976 962
The collection is open to research.
1888 Born in Chicago, Illinois, to Frank Elliott and Elizabeth T. (Dyer) Bell.
1903-1907 Attended John Dewey Laboratory School, University of Chicago High School.
1910 Graduate from Sargent School of Physical Education.
1910-1915 Taught at South Park Playground, Chicago.
1910-1916 Taught at Englewood High School.
1915 Graduated with B.S. from University of Chicago.
1916-1918 Taught at University of Chicago.
1918 Taught at Teachers' College, Chicago.
1920 Graduated from Trudeau School of Tuberculosis.
1921 Graduated with M.D. from Rush Medical School, Chicago; Assistant, Internal Medicine at Cardiac Clinics, Central Free Dispensary, Chicago.
1922 Research worker at Elizabeth McCormick Memorial Fund, Chicago.
1923 Received certificate from San Francisco Hospital, San Francisco.
1923 Co-director of Camp Tenaya, Yosemite, Ontario.
1923/24 Professor of Hygiene and Physical Education, Chairman Department of Physical Education for Women, Medical Advisor for Women at University of Michigan. (continued in these positions until 1956)
1929-1930 Instructor, Internal Medicine at University of Chicago Clinics.
1937-1938 New York Post Graduate School of medicine.
1969 Died
Professional and Service Organizations in Which Margaret Bell Was Active
Organizations:
Physical Education
American Association for Health and Physical Education
Mid-West Physical Education Association
Michigan Physical Education Association
National College Directors' Society
Midwest College Physical Education Society
Sargent Alumnae Association
Education:
Michigan Education Association
National Education Association
Medical:
American Medical Association
American Public Health Association
American Student Health Association
Michigan Student Health Association
National Conference on College Hygiene
Washtenaw County Medical Society
Others:
Women's Research Society
A.A.U.W.
University of Chicago Alumni and Alumnae Associations
American Youth Hostels
Honorary Societies:
Alpha Omega Alpha - Honorary Medical
Delta Omega - Honorary Public Health
Phi Kappa Phi - Honorary Education
Pi Lambda Theta - Honorary Education
Fellow, American Medical Association
Fellow, American College of Physicians (1932)
Fellow, American Association for Health and Physical Education (1933)
Fellow, American Public Health Association (1941)
Outside Committees and Responsibilities:
Physical Education
American Association for Health and Physical Education and Recreation
1929 Committee on Medical Examinations for Women and Girls
1935 Executive Committee
1935 Legislative Council
1935 Governing Board
1937 Vice-President
1932-33 Section Chairman, Therapeutic Section
1934-35 Section Chairman, Teacher Training Section
1934 Dance Section Adviser
1939-40 President
1944 Committee to establish provisions for Health Service Health Instruction, Physical Education, Athletics and Recreation for U.S. Office of Education
American Youth Hostels
Regional Committee
1938 Advisory Board, Great Lakes Area
Women's Athletic Section of American Association for Health and Physical Education
1931 Member of Executive Committee and Legislative Board
1934 Committee on Policy
1934 Finance Committee
1933-35 National College Directors' Society, Program Committee
1931-33 Mid-West College Directors' Society, President
Mid-West Physical Education Association
1930-32 Vice-President
1932-34 President
1933-34 Committee on Orthopedics
1935-36 Committee on Reorganization and Policy
State Council on Physical Education, 1934
Michigan Physical Education Association
1933-34 Advisory Committee
White House Committees
1929 Leadership Training in Secondary Schools
1929 Recreation and Physical Education
Medical and Health Education
Washtenaw County Medical Society
1936 Vice-President
1938-39 Committee on Public Health Legislation
American Student Health Association
1932-33 Committee on Physical Activities
1932-33 Committee on Program
1932-33 Women's Committee
1938- Committee on Hygiene of Physical Activities
Michigan Student Health Association
1936 Committee on Department Organization, Integration and Administration of Student Health
National Conference on College Hygiene
1932-33 Committee on Interrelations and Correlation of
Hea1th Conference called by Governor Murphy in Lansing, 1938
National Conference for Cooperation in School Health Education
1938 Member on Organization and Appraisal Committee
1939 Executive Committee, alternate member-at-large
American Association of School Administrators
1941-1942 Member, Commission on 1942 Yearbook on Health Education
The papers support the work and activities of Margaret Bell as Professor of Physical Education, Chairman of Department of Physical Education for Women, and a physician in Health Services at the University of Michigan from 1923 to 1956, and are divided into two sub-groups of personal activities and those specific to the University of Michigan.
The strength of the papers is found in the correspondence and reports which show the growth of physical education programs for women at the University and the identification of issues important to physical education and health in the 1930s, 1940s, and 1950s, with the correspondence, speeches, and publications of Margaret Bell. Historical records about the Women's Athletic Building and the Women's Athletic Association are also important.
Significant correspondents include: Amos Alonzo Stagg, John Dewey, and Elmer D. Mitchell, as well as other physical education professionals: Elizabeth Halsey, Ernest Jokl, Julian Smith, Ruth Glassow, Jay B. Nash, Charles Harold McCloy, Mable Lee, Vance Blanchard, and Charles Forsyth.
Topics of special note include the article, "Athletic Competition for Women," written for AAU March, 29, 1954, as well as other articles about the physiological effects of exercise and sport for women. During the 1950s and early 1960s college women participated in playdays and sportsdays, rather than the organized intercollegiate athletic programs of the present day. There was concern that women were not physically capable of such strenuous demands of full-court basketball and were limited by the rules to half-court play during the 1950's, with two rovers being added in the 1960's.
Subjects:
Bell, Margaret, 1888-1969.; Physical education for women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education for Women.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women--Health and hygiene--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Women.; Athletic fields--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children.; Clothing and dress--1920-1960.; Gymnasiums--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Physical education.; Sports.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education for Women.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; Women.
Contributors:
Bell, Margaret, 1888-1969.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Lee, Mabel.; Halsey, Elizabeth, b. 1890.; Jordan, Myra Beach, 1863-1946.; McCloy, Charles H. (Charles Harold), 1886-1959.; Mitchell, Elmer Dayton, 1889-; Nash, Jay Bryan, 1886-1965.; Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.; Stagg, Amos Alonzo, 1862-1965.; Sundwall, John, 1880-1950.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  - Biographical sketch, curriculum vita, etc. (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence
  Personal correspondence, 1926-1946, arranged chronologically by school year covers Margaret Bell's career at the University of Michigan. There are references to professional activities; however, the correspondence specifically related to professional assignments, such as departmental matters, speaking engagements or writings are filed with those subjects.
  - 1926/27 (Box 1)
  - 1927/28 (Box 1)
  - 1928/29 (Box 1)
  - 1929/30 (Box 1)
  - 1930/31 (Box 1)
  - 1931/32 (Box 1)
  - 1932/33 (Box 1)
  - 1933/34 (Box 1)
  - 1934/35 (Box 1)
  - 1935/36 (Box 1)
  - 1936/37 (Box 1)
  - 1937/38 (Box 1)
  - 1938/39 (Box 1)
  - 1940/41 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1946 (Box 1)
- Talks and requests
  Talks and requests, 1928-1955, arranged chronologically and include transcripts of talks and related correspondence.
  - 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1955 (Box 1)
- Talks 1936-1951
  The Talks series, 1928-1955, is arranged chronologically with each talk and related correspondence file in separate folders. the series includes talks at educational organizations, social clubs and conferences.
  - Iowa State University, Iowa City, Iowa February 24, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Progressive Education Association April 25, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Playground Leaders' Institute, Camp Keewano Wohelo, Ottawa Beach, Holland, Mich. June, 1936 (Box 2)
  - East Tennessee Education Association, October 26-28 1939 (Box 2)
  - University of West Virginia, Morgantown July 15, 1940 (Box 2)
  - 8th International New Education Fellowship Conference, Ann Arbor, Mich. July 6-12, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Representative Women's Clubs, Cleveland, Ohio February 14, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Kiwanis Club, Battle Creek, Mich. February 19, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Jackson High School, Jackson, Mich. March 3, 1942 (Box 2)
  - 6th Annual Vocations Conference, Michigan State University, East Lansing April 22, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Seminar sponsored by Northwestern University and Office of Management Association of Chicago April 24, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Radio talk, University of Michigan May 1, 1942 10:30 p.m. (Box 2)
  - Occupational Conference, "The Role of Women in the War Effort," University of Michigan, Ann Arbor January 6-8, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Alumnae Council Group, Monroe, Mich. January 19, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Women in a Defense Decade Conference, New York City Sept 27-28 1941 (correspondence and handouts three folders) (Box 2)
- Articles
  Articles, 1930-1954, chronologically, with some articles included in the notebooks of the publication series.
  - Correspondence 1930-1944 (Box 2)
  - Sargent Quarterly News Bulletin, 1930, 1933, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Athletic Competition for Women March 29, 1954 (Box 2)
- Publications
  Publications, 1929-1954, arranged chronologically in three notebooks, with drafts or, publications in which articles are included. Bibliography of publications included in front of Box 3.
  - Notebooks 1929-1954, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - Correspondence relating to 1942 Yearbook of the American Association of School Administrators 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - Requests for collaboration 1941, 1945 (Box 3)
  - The Hygiene of marriage (Box 3)
- Extra-University Appointments
  The Extra-university appointments series, 1931-1956, is arranged chronologically by organization and consists primarily of correspondence. The AAHPER Fitness Conference in Washington, D. C., Sept, 12-15, 1956 includes statements on physical fitness by well-known professionals - Dr. Elmer Mitchell is one of the participants.
  - Eastern Michigan Water Carnival Association 1931 (Box 4)
  - Dancing Masters of America 1942/43 (Box 4)
  - Southeastern Michigan Recreation Project, Dept. of Conservation 1943/44 (Box 4)
  - American Association of Health, Physical Education and Recreation, Committee on Affiliated Organizations 1949/50 (Box 4)
  - Wayne-Washtenaw-Macomb County Coordinating Committee on Recreation 1943/44 (Box 4)
  - Willow Run Recreational Project 1943/44 (Box 4)
  - National Council on Physical Fitness 1944/45 (Box 4)
  - Commission on Place of Calisthenics in Physical Fitness 1945-1945 (Box 4)
  - Co-Chairman, Programming Section on School and Colleges, Joint Effort American Medical Association and National Council on Physical Fitness 1944 (declined) (Box 4)
  - Committee on Physical Fitness and Commission on Physical Fitness for Women 1944/45 (Box 4)
  - Medical Advisor to Committee on Physical Fitness (Box 4)
  - U. S. Office of Education, Committee for Establishing Provisions of Health Services, Health Instruction, Physical Education, Athletics, and Recreation 1944/45 (Box 4)
  - Advisory Committee on Health, Physical Education, Recreation, School Camping and Outdoor Education, Michigan Department of Public Instruction 1945/46 (Box 4)
  - National Education Association and American Medical Association, Joint Committee on Health Problems in Education 1947-1951 (Box 4)
  - Educational Policies Committee 1949-1951 (Box 4)
  - Midwest Association of College Teachers of Physical Education for Women 1949-1951 (Box 4)
  - American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation Fitness Conference, Washington, D. C. September 12-15, 1956 (Box 4)
  - The American College of Sports Medicine 1956 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1943-1956 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Files
  The Miscellaneous files series includes school grade reports, certification records, contracts, etc. and Ann Arbor Golf and Outing Club memberships lists, 1934-1936.
  - Ann Arbor Golf and Outing Club 1934-1936 (Box 4)
  - School grade reports, certification records, contracts (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (personal) (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series is arranged by subject, including: campus scenes; colleagues and friends; dancing; medical subjects; portraits; sports: archery, basketball, volleyball, fencing, golf, gym, field hockey, riding, swimming, diving, tennis, and track. In the colleagues and friends folder are pictures of Dr. Henry Montoye and Dr. Jay B. Nash.
  - Campus scenes, biking, picnicking (Box 4)
  - Colleagues, friends (Box 4)
  - Dancing (Box 4)
  - Medical subjects (Box 4)
  - Portraits (Box 4)
  - Sports: archery (Box 4)
  - Sports: basketball, volleyball (Box 4)
  - Sports: fencing, golf, gym, field hockey, riding (Box 4)
  - Sports: swimming, diving (Box 4)
  - Sports: tennis, track (Box 4)
- University of Michigan Material
  The University of Michigan Material series includes files documenting Bell's teaching and administrative work.
  - Michigan League
    Michigan League files, 1937-1950, include newspaper clippings on scrapbook sheets arranged chronologically. Bell was on the Board of Directors of the Michigan League. \
    - 1937-1942 (Box 4)
    - 1943-1947 (Box 4)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Dr. John Sundwall, Chairman of the Division of Hygiene, Public Health, Physical Education
    Correspondence, 1924-1939, with Dr. John Sundwall, Chairman of the Division of Hygiene, Public Health, Physical Education arranged chronologically and mainly covering department concerns.
    - 1924/25, 1927/28-1928/29 (Box 5)
    - 1929/30-1930/31 (Box 5)
    - 1931/32-1932/33 (Box 5)
    - 1933/34-1935/36 (Box 5)
    - 1936/37-1938/39 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with the President's Office
    Correspondence, 1919-1936, with President's Office, arranged chronologically. Includes mainly requests from physical education faculty to attend professional meetings.
    - 1919-1930 (Box 5)
    - 1931-1936 (Box 5)
  - Department of Physical Education for Women
    Department of Physical Education for Women, 1924-1941, arranged by topic, beginning with history of the department (1895-1924); administration (1926-1928); reorganization plan (1941-1942); graduate programs (1931-1939); departmental studies (1940-941); tests (1922-1954); required physical education (1919-1941); extramural competition (1937-1941); camp; and publicity (1928-1970). Correspondence and reports provide the bulk of the information.
    - History 1895-1924 (Box 5)
    - Administration 1926/27-1927/28 (Box 5)
    - Regents' proceedings 1914-1929 (Box 5)
    - Reorganization plan 1941-1942 (Box 5)
    - Graduate program 1931-1939 (Box 5)
    - Master's theses 1934-1940 (Box 5)
    - Departmental studies 1940-1941 (Box 5)
    - Required physical education
      - 1919-1938 (Box 5)
      - 1939-1941 (Box 5)
    - Tests
      - 1922-1939 (Box 5)
      - 1930-1954 (Box 5)
    - Extramural competition 1937-1941 (Box 5)
    - Camp 1926-1935 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1926-1928, 1936, 1940-1941 (Box 5)
    - Publicity
      - 1928-1939 (Box 6)
      - 1949-1962 (Box 6)
      - 1963-1967 (Box 6)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Barbour Gymnasium-Budget records 1918/19-1922/23 (Box 6)
  - Women's Athletic Building
    - 1925-1927 (Box 6)
    - 1928 (January-February) (Box 6)
    - 1929 (Box 6)
    - 1930-1933 (Box 6)
    - 1935-1937 (Box 6)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 6)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 6)
  - Palmer Field, 1928-1930, History (Box 6)
    The Palmer Filed file, 1928-30 includes letter from Dean Emeritus, Myra B. Jordan, in which she Identifies Senator Thomas Palmer of Detroit as the person who gave President Angell the money for the field.
  - Women's Athletic Association
    Women's Athletic Association files, 1925-1940, are arranged by subject, including: history and constitution (1925-1928); president and treasurer's reports (1928-1932); and programs and publicity materials for Lantern Night (1924-1940), a program performed by students of the University of Michigan and sponsored by WAA and the freshman class. Cabin plans also included.
    - History and constitution 1925/26-1927/28 (Box 6)
    - President and treasurer's reports 1928/29-1931/32 (Box 6)
    - Lantern Night 1924-1940 (Box 6)
    - Cabin plans 1931-1933 (Box 6)
  - School of Education
    The School of Education files, 1928-1941, consists of correspondence arranged chronologically. Letters and reports come mainly from Dean J. B. Edmunson.
    - 1928-1932 (Box 6)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 6)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 6)
    - 1937-1939 (Box 6)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan Health Service 1928-1930 (Box 6)
  - Committee on the Defense Training Program for Women 1941-1943 (Box 6)